Guide to the George Wilson Pierson Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
George Wilson Pierson papers
1820-1991
MS 401
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
175.5
The papers consist of office files which contain notes on courses taken at Yale, teaching and faculty materials, manuscripts, typescripts, correspondence, subject and research files, and professional organizations materials. The bulk of the material relates to his work on the history of Yale and the National Endowment for the Humanities project.
Pierson, George Wilson, 1904-1993
Conditions Governing Access
Accession 1994-M-012 is unprocessed and may contain sensitive information or be in a physical state that would prohibit use. Researchers wishing to request access should email mssa.assist@yale.edu requesting specific box numbers in order to initiate the review process, which may take several weeks.
All other material is open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of George W. Pierson, 1973, 1988, 1989, 1991, and 1993. Gift of the Estate of George W. Pierson, 1995. Gift of Radley H. Daly, 1990. Transferred from the Bibliography Department, 1988. Transferred from the John Farquhar Fulton Papers, 1996. Transferred from YRG 2-A-17, 1999.
Biographical / Historical
George Wilson Pierson received his B.A. from Yale in 1926 and his Ph.D. in 1933. He became a member of the faculty of Yale University in 1926, holding the positions of professor of history, 1944-1946; Larned professor of history, 1946-1973; and emeritus since 1973. Pierson was also historian of Yale University and the author of many books. He died on October 12, 1993.
Scope and Contents
The papers consist of office files which contain notes on courses taken at Yale, teaching and faculty materials, manuscripts, typescripts, correspondence, subject and research files, and professional organizations materials. The bulk of the material relates to his work on the history of Yale and the National Endowment for the Humanities project.
History; Historians; Aldrich, Malcolm Pratt, 1900-; Angell, James Rowland, 1869-1949; Aswell, Edward C. (Edward Campbell), 1900-1958; Cant, Ronald Gordon; Fisher, Samuel H. (Samuel Herbert), 1867-1957; Harkness, Edward Stephen, 1874-1940; Pierson, George Wilson, 1904-1993; Seymour, Charles, 1885-1963; American Council of Learned Societies; National Endowment for the Humanities; Old Dominion Foundation; Yale University -- Faculty; Yale University -- History
- Inventory
  - Notes on courses in Yale College, 1922-1926 (Box 1)
  - Notes on courses taken in Yale Graduate School, 1927-1931 (Box 1)
  - Notes on U.S. History (Hist. 20), 1929-1930, et. seg. (Box 1)
  - Notes on U.S. History (Hist. 20), 1929-1930, et. seg. (Box 2)
  - Notes on U.S. History (Hist. 20), 1929-1930, et. seg. (Box 3)
  - Notes on U.S. History (Hist. 20), 1929-1930 (Box 4)
  - Old course notes from Groton School, 1918-1922 (Box 4)
  - Old course notes (Box 5)
  - Old course notes: (Box 6)
    General
    Hist. 39
    Hist. 33
    Hist. 20
    Davenport
    History Majors and Departmental Reserves
    Grade books
    Student Papers
    History Ph.D. Questionaires
  - Yale History
    General note
    Administration
    History Committee
    LUNT criticism
    Yale presidents
    Secretaries
    Expenses
    Bursary students and jobs
    Tables for Vol. II
    Notes of conversations
    - Vol. I - MSS (first long version) revised MSS (Box 7)
    - Vol. I - MSS (first long version) revised MSS (Box 8)
    - Vol. I - MSS (first long version) revised MSS (Box 9)
    - Vol. II - chapter drafts (Box 10)
    - Vol. II - chapter drafts (Box 11)
    - Vol. II - chapter drafts: Typescripts and revisions (Box 12)
    - Vol. II - chapter drafts: Typescripts and revisions (Box 12a)
    - Vol. I - typescripts and revisions (Box 13)
    - Vol. I - typescripts and revisions (Box 14)
    - Vol. II - typescripts and revisions (Box 15)
    - Vol. II:- notes: (Box 16)
    - Notes of conversations (Box 17)
  - Education of American Leaders
    - Bursary job materials (Box 18)
    - Bursary job materials (Box 19)
    - Bursary job materials (Box 20)
    - Manuscripts and table folders (Box 21)
    - Table folders (Box 22)
    - Table folders (Box 23)
    - Table folders (Box 24)
  - National Endowment for the Humanities Project
    - History of the Humanities (Box 25)
    - Correspondence (Box 25)
    - History of the Humanities, 1964-1970 (Box 26)
    - Executive Committee of Faculty of A & S (Box 26)
    - General and Special Projects (Box 26)
    - Division of the Humanities (Box 27)
    - Departments (Box 27)
    - Departments (Box 28)
    - Division of the Humanities (Box 29)
    - Departments (Box 29)
    - Microfilm (Box 29)
  - Computer for the Humanities?(1965)
    - Recordings (Box 29)
    - Recordings (Box 30)
  - Graduate School Conference
    - Records (Box 30)
    - Book (Box 30)
  - Division of the Humanities
    - Committee Meeting (Box 31)
    - Areas and Special programs (Box 31)
  - Files on Library Affairs (Box 31)
  - Files on Library Affairs (Box 32)
  - Old Dominion Foundation (1966-1970)/ Advisory materials (Box 32)
  - Old Dominion Foundation/ Advisory materials (Box 33)
  - American Council of Learned Societies/ Correspondence- projects-documnets on delegates to AHA, 1962-1970 (Box 34)
  - Liberal Arts Campaign (1942-1944) (Box 35)
  - Research material for Yale: College and University, 1871-1957 (Box 36–37)
    Box 36 includes files on the Corporation's Architectural Plan Committee, 1920-1931, and on the Alumni Committee on University Plan, 1917-1920. Box 37 includes files on The Commonwealth Fund, and on the Residential College Plan, 1910-1939.
  - Materials by and about Oliver T. Osborne (1862-1940, Y. 1884m) (Box 37)
  - Re: Alfred Van Sinderen; Samuel Russel; Clive Day (Box 37)
- Additional Material, 1929-1986; Accession 1988-M-088; 11.5 linear feet (12 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  Addition inventory by Carol King 1988 June
  Received from George W. Pierson, 1988 May 16
  - Faculty Concerns
    - Brewster, Kingman, 1968-1969 (Box 1)
    - Brewster, Kingman, 1970-1973 (Box 1)
    - Brewster, Kingman, 1963-1972 (Box 1)
    - Bockelman, Charles K., 1969 (Box 1)
    - Coffin, William Sloane, Jr., 1968 (Box 1)
    - Davison, Endicott (Cottie), 1971 (Box 1)
    - Ecklund, John and Yale finances, 1971 (Box 1)
    - Holden, Reuben (Ben), 1963-1972 (Box 1)
    - Kahn, Herman, 1968-1969 (Box 1)
    - MacLeish, William H., 1969 (Box 1)
    - Paul Mellon Gallery of British Art and Center for British Studies, 1968 (Box 1)
    - May, Georges and Yale College, 1963-1967 (Box 1)
    - Yale College Dean, 1967-1968 (Box 1)
    - Miller, John Perry, 1967-1968 (Box 1)
    - Miller, John Perry, 1968-1969 (Box 1)
    - Phelan, Howard and University Development, 1968-1969 (Box 1)
    - Taft, Horace/Yale College, 1971-1972 (Box 1)
    - Taylor, Charles H., 1971-1972 (Box 1)
    - Taylor, Charles H., (Provost), 1964 (Box 1)
    - Taylor, Donald, 1969-1971 (Box 1)
    - Graduate School Faculty, 1964 (Box 1)
    - Graduate Fellowships, 1963 (Box 1)
    - Carnegie Teaching Fellows, 1963 (Box 1)
    - Morse Fellowships, 1963 (Box 1)
    - Joint Committee on the BA-MA Degree, 1965-1972 (Box 1)
    - Alumni Seminars, 1959-1965 (Box 1)
    - Humanities Advisory Committee (HAC): Alumni Seminar?: "University in American Society", 1957-1970 (Box 1)
    - Davenport College, 1946-1966 (Box 1)
    - Labaree, Leonard W./Franklin papers editorship, 1968-1969 (Box 1)
    - Lerner/Yale Movie, 1966 (Box 1)
    - Yale Information Center, undated (Box 1)
    - New Colleges-names, 1972 (Box 1)
    - Ivory Tower Blues, 1970 (Box 1)
    - Chairs (Endowed), 1969-1971 (Box 1)
    - Notestein, Wallace (Professorship), 1963-1975 (Box 1)
    - Yale College, Yale University: Humanities: Unfinished Ventures, 1967 (Box 1)
    - Congress: 18th Century Studies, 1969-1971 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence on University Affairs, 1946-1971 (Box 1)
    - Dahl Report, 1971-1972 (Box 1)
    - Blum-Pelikan Group "Old Savings and New Causes", 1971-1972 (Box 1)
    - Humanities and NEH (National Endowment for Humanities) and Yale, 1972-1974 (Box 1)
    - AAUP (American Association of University Professors) and ACLU (American Civil Liberties Union), 1963-1969 (Box 1)
    - Yale Information System, 1966-1971 (Box 1)
    - Wu, Nelson I., 1964-1968 (Box 1)
    - Lynd, Staughton, 1966-1968 (Box 1)
    - Bernstein, Richard, 1965 (Box 1)
    - Mills, Kenneth, 1972 (Box 1)
    - Coeducation for Yale, 1966-1968 (Box 1)
    - Coeducation, 1966-1968 (Box 2)
    - Coeducation, 1968-1971 (Box 2)
    - Outside articles and correspondence on Yale student troubles, 1969 (Box 2)
    - ROTC, 1970-1971 (Box 2)
    - Blacks, 1970 (Box 2)
    - Blacks, 1968-1969 (Box 2)
    - Vietnam, 1965 (Box 2)
    - Students vs. Yale, 1969-1970 (Box 2)
    - Students vs. Yale, 1969-1970 (Box 2)
    - Yale Buildings, 1968-1970 (Box 2)
    - Calendar (recess time), 1970-1971 (Box 2)
    - Yale College-Discipline, 1969-1970 (Box 2)
    - Yale College Faculty and Committee of Study, 1969-1970 (Box 2)
    - Yale College Faculty Policies, 1969-1972 (Box 2)
    - Moore Fund, 1966-1972 (Box 2)
    - Grades: Pass, Fail, etc., 1969-1970 (Box 2)
    - Yale College Spring Grades '70: m-f p-s, 1969-1971 (Box 2)
    - Graduate faculty, 1969-1970 (Box 2)
    - Library 1970: Advisory Council (Box 2)
    - Library 1970-1971 (Box 2)
    - Secretary: BPO (Boards of Permanent Officers of Yale College and the Graduate School) '72-'73, 1973 (Box 2)
    - Secretary: BPO minutes-G.W.P., 1971-1972 (Box 2)
    - Yale College [Faculty] Steering Committee: Spring 1972 (Box 2)
  - Yale Historical Documents and Letters
    - Correspondence, 1976-1979 (Box 3)
    - Seminar on History of Yale College, 1979 (Box 3)
    - Andrew, Samuel, 1977 (Box 3)
    - Correspondence, 1977-1981 (Box 3)
    - Rose, Frederick P., 1972-1974 (Box 3)
    - Correspondence, 1972-1984 (Box 3)
    - Thelin, John R. and Lilienthal, Philip E., 1973-1977 (Box 3)
    - Correspondence, 1974 (Box 3)
    - Davis, Ronald A., 1974 (Box 3)
    - Yale and England, 1974-1975 (Box 3)
    - Silliman Records, 1973 (Box 3)
    - Luce, Henry, 1974-1975 (Box 3)
    - Sigma XI Research, 1973 (Box 3)
    - Hale, Nathan, 1973 (Box 3)
    - Clipping, pamphlets, 1974-1977 (Box 3)
    - Belgian Bicentennial TV, 1974 (Box 3)
    - Pennsylvania Conference on Undergraduate Education, 1974 (Box 3)
    - Clippings, pamphlets, 1975-1984 (Box 3)
  - ISPS (Institution for Social and Policy Studies)
    - ISPS-Higher Education Seminar, 1974 (Box 6)
    - Papers pertaining to colloquium on higher education, 1974 (Box 6)
    - News clippings, pamphlets, 1970-1973 (Box 6)
    - Hall, Peter, 1973 (Box 6)
    - ISPS, 1973 (Box 6)
    - Professional Education, 1973 (Box 6)
    - Meetings ISS (Institute of Social Science) #489, 1971-1972 (Box 6)
    - Higher education statistics, 1973-1974 (Box 6)
    - ISPS, 1973 (Box 6)
    - ISPS-post-doctorals in higher education, 1973 (Box 6)
    - Hoeveler, David J., Jr., 1972-1973 (Box 6)
    - Miller, John Perry, 1972 (Box 6)
    - Project for study of higher education center for the study of education in the Institution for Social and Policy Studies at Yale University, 1972 (Box 6)
    - ISPS-post-doctoral search, 1972-1973 (Box 6)
    - ISPS-correspondence, articles, 1972-1973 (Box 6)
    - Social Science Institute, 1969-1971 (Box 6)
    - Miller, John Perry, Seminar on Comparative Higher Education: plans, ideas, 1969-1972 (Box 6)
    - Urban studies, 1970-1971 (Box 6)
    - Assorted papers re: higher education, 1972-1974 (Box 6)
  - Class of 1926-1926S and Yale Graduate School Alumni
    - Poster "Help restore Elihu Yale's organ", 1984 (Box 7)
    - Yale Graduate School Alumni Fund Committees, 1978-1983 (Box 7)
    - Yale Graduate School Association Meetings, 1979-1980 (Box 7)
    - Executive Committee: Yale Graduate School Association, 1974-1979 (Box 7)
    - Alumni Fund: Graduate School, 1972-1980 (Box 7)
    - Graduate School Alumni Association, 1963-1976 (Box 7)
    - CFY (Campaign for Yale): Graduate School, 1976 (Box 7)
    - 1926 (Class of) Alumni Fund, 1970-1972 (Box 7)
    - Joyce, Robert, 1969-1971 (Box 7)
    - Stoddard, Carlos French, 1987 (Box 7)
    - Condolences, memorials, 1982-1986 (Box 7)
    - 1926 (Class of) Memorial Agent, 1979-1982 (Box 7)
    - 1926-1926S, 1979-1980 (Box 7)
    - 1926-1926S Reunion Planning, 1980-1986 (Box 7)
    - Class of 1926-1926S, 1957-1980 (Box 7)
  - AYA (Association of Yale Alumni) and Yale Alumni Fund (YAF)
    - Various copies of Yale Alumni Magazine, 1970-1981 (Box 8)
    - Two packets relating to AYA workshops, 1984-1985 (Box 8)
    - Yale Alumni Fund Annual Report, 1980-1981 (Box 8)
    - Papers, pamphlets re: AYA, YAF, 1977-1986 (Box 8)
    - YAF Annual report "Bequest and Endowment Program", 1982-1983 (Box 8)
    - YAF Annual Report "Bequest and Endowment Program", 1981-1982 (Box 8)
    - Achieving Financial Equilibrium at Yale: a report on the budget, 1977 (Box 8)
    - Report to the Yale Alumni on alumni activities, 1972-1973 (Box 8)
    - Bicentennial, 1972-1976 (Box 8)
    - Alumni Fund, etc., 1973-1976 (Box 8)
    - AYA, 1973-1975 (Box 8)
    - NIH (National Humanities Institute), 1974-1977 (Box 8)
    - Endowment Drive, 1974-1976 (Box 8)
    - Marshman, Donald M., Jr., 1974-1976 (Box 8)
    - Roel, Ronald E.: CFY Business Gifts, 1974-1975 (Box 8)
    - Yale University Bicentennial Committee, 1976 (Box 8)
    - Clippings, pamphlets, CFY, 1974-1976 (Box 8)
    - "What is Yale?", 1974-1976 (Box 9)
    - Prospectus of Yale, 1975 (Box 9)
    - Several brochures: School of Forestry, Yale Glee Club, etc., 1975-1976 (Box 9)
    - Questions from Yale and Prospectus, 1974 (Box 9)
    - Report of the Commission on Alumni Affairs, 1970 (Box 9)
    - Yale and Alumni, 1969-1972 (Box 9)
    - Admissions, 1966-1972 (Box 9)
    - Billington Letter, 1971 (Box 9)
    - Annual report: Henry Luce Foundation, 1970 (Box 9)
    - Slater, Thomas Operation Watchdog, 1970 (Box 9)
    - Various papers re: admissions, 1971-1972 (Box 9)
    - "Old Blues: past, present, future" A plan for alumni relations, 1971 (Box 9)
    - Yale Alumni Fund (Box 9)
    - Various reports-AYA (Box 9)
    - "Newport in 1780", 1978 (Box 9)
  - Kelley, Brooks: typescript of Yale: A History, I, II (Box 9)
  - Book manuscripts about Yale by others
    - Oren, Dan A.: A History of Jews and Yale and related papers, 1980-1985 (Box 10)
    - Catlin, Daniel Jr.: Liberal Education at Yale, 1981-1982 (Box 10)
    - Richard, David Alan: "The Making of the Corporation 1969" and "Yale Scene Series" papers, 1969-1974 (Box 10)
    - Typescript "The Making of the Corporation 1969", 1973 (Box 10)
    - Bledstein, Burton J. on: Noah Porter and Herbert Spencer, 1974-1975 (Box 10)
    - Bledstein, Burton J. Mid-Victorian Americans typescript (Box 10)
    - Thelin, John R. Images of the Ivy League, 1890 to 1960, 1973 (Box 10)
    - Noss, Luther: History of the Yale School of Music, 1848-1970, 1979 (Box 10)
    - O'Connor, Thomas: dissertation proposal for History of the Yale University Library, 1865-1931, 1981 (Box 10)
    - Noss, Luther. "Yale University Faculty Appointments in Music 1890-1970", 1981 (Box 10)
    - Noss, Luther: "Yale School of Music"
      - Prologue: 1855-1890 and chapter I: 1890-1894, 1980 (Box 10)
      - Chapter II: 1894-1919, 1981 (Box 10)
      - Chapter III: 1919-1940, 1981 (Box 10)
      - Chapter IV: 1940-1941, 1981 (Box 10)
      - Chapter V: 1941-1954, 1982 (Box 10)
      - Chapter VI: 1954-1970, 1983 (Box 10)
      - Appendix, index, 1983 (Box 10)
  - Wilbur Lucius Cross Medal
    - Wilbur Cross Medal (WCM), 1974-1975 (Box 11)
    - Wilbur Cross Medal nominees, 1984-1985 (Box 11)
    - Graduate Medal (Wilbur Cross), 1966-1970 (Box 11)
    - Nominees for Wilbur Cross Medal, 1985-1986 (Box 11)
    - Model of medal, undated (Box 11)
  - Printed material and articles, reprints by others
    - Davenport directory, 1973-1974 (Box 12)
    - Dater, Henry M. "Aviation in the Antarctic", 1959 (Box 12)
    - Photograph-signed Curt Faber, undated (Box 12)
    - Weaver, Glenn (pamphlet entitled "The Schwenkfelders during the French and Indian War", 1955 (Box 12)
    - Threee copies of "The Moderator", 1963-1964 (Box 12)
    - Asakawa, K. "The Early Sho and the Early Manor: A Comparative Study", 1929 (Box 12)
    - Asakawa, K. "Agriculture in Japanese History", 1929 (Box 12)
    - Yale University Library Gazette, 1934 October (Box 12)
    - Asakawa, K. "Japanese feudalism", 1931 (Box 12)
    - Mitchell, Sydney K. "Phases of the History of Cornwall", undated (Box 12)
    - Bestor, Arthur "State sovereignty and slavery", 1961 (Box 12)
    - Morse, Richard M. "The Protéstant Ethic and the Non-Protestant World: a challenge for foreign area studies", 1965 (Box 12)
    - "Caribbean studies" (two papers), 1961 (Box 12)
    - Owen, David. "A memorandum on the problem of placement", undated (Box 12)
    - Powell, J.H. "The American Revolution: a framework for thinking", 1942-1943 (Box 12)
    - "Paul Revere's three accounts of his famous ride", 1961 (Box 12)
    - Giamatti, A. Bartlett: AYA Assembly XIX Dinner address, 1981 (Box 12)
    - Fishwick, Marshall W. "Textbooks and American History", 1963 (Box 12)
    - Hexter, J.H. "Storm over the Gentry" (on the Great Rebellion-England-1640s), undated (Box 12)
    - Keller, Charles R. Papers on advanced placement, 1958 (Box 12)
    - Wolfers, Arnold. "Some considerations affecting the peace settlement with Germany", 1944 (Box 12)
  - An "Interview" with George Pierson, 1988 March 2 (Box 12)
  - Questions with George Pierson concerning Franklin Dexter and his work, 1988 March 2 (Box 12)
  - Tape of interview (Box 12)
- Additional Material, 1988 March 2; Accession 1989-M-022; 3
  Addition Inventory by Carol King 1989 January
  Received from: Susanne Roberts, editor Nota Bene; News from the Yale Library, 1988 Jul 1
- Additional Material, 1933; Accession 1989-M-087; 0.25; (1 box)
  Addition Inventory by Carol King 1989 June
  Received from; George W. Pierson, 1989 May 16
  - Two Frenchmen in America, 1831-1832: theStudies and Adventures of Alexis de Tocqueville and Gustave deBeaumont in the United States and Canada -with-the Story of the Origins and Development of Tocqueville's "Democracy in America" from their letters, diaries, and sketches [by George Pierson]., 1933 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - (The first eight chapters of a proposed book submitted in competition for the John Addison Porter Prize.) (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Material pertaining to the founding of Yale College at Old Saybrook, 1989, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Additional Material, 1989, undated; Accession 1990-M-053; 1
  Received from: Radley H. Daly, 1990 Jan 19
- Additional Material, 1988-1989; Accession 1992-M-030; 1
  Addition inventory by Carol King 1992 Jan
  Received from: George W. Pierson, 1989 Feb 7
  - Correspondence with Alfred W. Van Sinderen pertaining to G. W. Pierson's book, The Founding of Yale, the Russel family, Rev. Samuel Russel, the ritual of the book-giving, and Samuel Russel as the "keeper of the books", 1988 December 12-1989 January 20 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Audio cassette containing an interview with G. W. Pierson on the occasion of the 290th anniversary of Yale, prepared by the Washington bureau of the German Radio Service (tape has been dubbed in German), 1991 October 9 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Additional Material, 1991; Accession 1992-M-038; 1
  Received from: George W. Pierson, 1991 Oct 31
- Additional Material, Circa 1969-circa 1993; Accession 1994-M-012
  Conditions Governing Access
  The material is unprocessed and may contain sensitive information or be in a physical state that would prohibit use. Researchers wishing to request access should email mssa.assist@yale.edu requesting specific box numbers in order to initiate the review process, which may take several weeks.
  Appraisal
  Boxes 23, 24, 27-29, 44-46, 50-52 are no longer in collection.
  - Materials related to The Founding of Yale. (Box 1–3)
  - Yale historical correspondence - topical (Box 4)
  - "The Time of Troubles, 1969-1970 and after" (Box 5)
  - Correspondence (Box 6)
  - Correspondence - Yale faculty and students (Box 7)
  - John S. Whitehead and James T. Schleifer (Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous files and unsorted correspondence (Box 9)
  - Courses and students: History 33 - History 39: Foreign Relations of American Culture (Box 10–11)
  - Courses and students: Graduate courses (Box 12–13)
  - Courses and students: The American Character (Box 14)
  - Courses and students: The American Character (continued) (Box 15)
  - Yale University Press [?] (Box 15)
  - Yale Alumni Magazine [?] (Box 16)
  - Student and faculty concerns (Box 16)
  - Student and faculty concerns (continued) (Box 17)
  - Writings and speeches (Box 17)
  - Writings and speeches (continued) (Box 18)
  - Correspondence (Box 18)
  - Correspondence (continued) (Box 19–20)
  - Correspondence (continued) (Box 21)
  - Materials related to The Moving American (Box 21)
  - Materials related to The Moving American (continued) (Box 22)
  - Materials related to Tocqueville (Box 25–26)
  - Early correspondence (Box 30–31)
  - Tocqueville correspondence (Box 32–33)
    Materials to be discarded, card files with bibliographic notes (4 boxes), bluebooks, publications.
  - (Restricted) Personnel, Fund, Office Records, 1970s - current. (Box 34)
  - Yale Historical Statistics: Possible topics, tables, etc. (Box 35)
  - Yale Historical Statistics: Possible topics, tables, etc. (Box 36)
  - Yale Historical Statistics: Possible topics, tables, etc. (Box 37)
  - Tables on Yale Eminence, DAB, Who's Who (Box 37)
  - Tables on Yale Eminence, DAB, Who's Who (Box 38)
  - Yale History Department (Box 39)
  - Yale History Department (Box 40)
  - Volume III, History of Yale: Plans, Chapters, Drafts. (Box 41)
  - Volume III, History of Yale: Plans, Chapters, Drafts. (Box 42)
  - Yale Book of Numbers (Box 43)
  - Yale Book of Numbers (Box 47)
  - Various Depts., Schools, Bldgs, etc. (Box 47)
  - Various Depts., Schools, Bldgs, etc. (Box 48)
  - Various Depts., Schools, Bldgs, etc. (Box 49)
  - Yale Buildings (Box 49)
  - Personal papers, Yale History Office budgets (Box 53)
  - CARD FILE BOXES
    - notes on Yale history, interviews, etc. (Box 54–91)
- Additional Material, Accession 1997-M-184
  - Chapter drafts for book, Circa 1950 (Box 1)
- Additional Material, Accession 1996-M-047
  This addition is composed of personal and family papers, including correspondence, diaries, memorabilia, legal and financial files, and photographs. The papers relate to George Pierson's parents and aunt, Eliza Day Pierson, who lived in Florida, NY. The papers also document George Pierson's education and travels in Europe.
  - Family correspondence and other family papers (Box 1)
  - GWP's student notebooks [high school?] (Box 1)
  - Photographs and negatives (Box 1)
  - Legal and financial files (Box 1)
  - Correspondence [incoming and outgoing], 1933-1943 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence [incoming], 1930-1940 (Box 3)
  - Letters received [letterbox], 1930/1931 (Box 4)
  - Family correspondence [in envelopes in packets], 19 (th) and 20 (th) centuries (Box 4)
  - Letters, general [letterbox], 1944 Spring (Box 5)
  - Yale scrapbook, 1923-1926 (Box 5)
  - Course materials, Yale, 1920s (Box 5)
  - Correspondence [in envelopes in packets], newspapers, and other papers of Eliza D. Pierson, 19(th) and 20(th) centuries (Box 6)
  - Account books, correspondence, and student papers of Charles Wheeler Pierson [father of GWP] (Box 7)
  - Student notebooks, diaries of Eliza Day Pierson [GWP's aunt] (Box 7)
  - Correspondence of Sarah Wheeler [GWP's grandmother?], 1860s (Box 7)
  - Family correspondence, 1900s (Box 7)
  - Unsorted family letters (Box 7)